Hi everyone, welcome back to
the IELTS Reading 4.0 - 5.0 at PREP.
Today we gonna learn about the question type
that has been with us since we started learning English.
Fill in the blanks or Completion.
But wait, you think you know it all,
but in fact, you don't.
This question type in IELTS is very different
from the gap-filling exercises we did in the past.
Let's find out the differences together.
Today's lesson aims to help you understand different
formats of completion questions in IELTS Reading.
Remember, understand and apply steps
for completion questions effectively.
We have three parts of the lesson.
1. Definition and formats of completion questions.
2. Effective steps for completion questions.
And 3. Practice.
All right, we're going to get to the
bottom of it together.
Are you ready?
Let's go.
Basically, completion questions in IELTS Reading are
gap-filling exercises based on the question's requirements.
However, there are two big differences between completion questions
and gap-filling exercises that we usually do.
Firstly, for completion questions, the answers must be
taken from the reading passage.
Normally, when we do gap-filling exercises, we
have to think about the words we want
to write or choose from an available list.
Or, with multiple choice questions,
we have four options for each blank.
In IELTS exams, it's different.
Let's look at this question.
Choose from the passage.
The question clearly says that the answers have
to be taken from the reading and you
can't write whatever you want.
There is only one type of completion that
does not follow this rule.
We will learn more about it in the next lesson.
Because of this specific requirement, you should pay
attention to these three DON'Ts when choosing the answer.
Don't change the path of speech.
Don't change the order.
And, don't change the singular into the plural
and vice versa.
Simply speaking, the answers in the blanks must
be exactly the same as those in the
reading passage, without any changes.
In fact, this requirement helps us check if
the answers are correct or not.
For example, the answer needs a singular noun.
When scanning in the passage, we found a
noun which has a suitable meaning, but it
turns out to be a plural noun.
It means that this word is not the one we need.
There are many students who will still try
to remove the plural form of this word
and write it in the blank, but it isn't correct.
It's not the answer we need.
The second difference compared to the traditional gap-filling exercises
is that in the IELTS reading,
there are seven formats of completion questions.
In IELTS reading, instead of filling words into
a paragraph, we also have to fill in
sentences, tables, or diagrams.
To sum up, I would like to introduce
to you the completion tree, a summary tree
of completion questions.
I'm going to divide them into two big groups.
The first group is questions with the answers come in order.
The second group is the questions
with the answers might not come in order.
In the first group, the answer to question 1
will appear before the answer to question 2, and so on.
In the second group, most of the answers
come in order, but there are some exercises
in which the answer to question 2 may
appear before the answer to question 1.
Questions with the answer come in order are easier,
because we can use this order to
locate the information for the questions
that we have not finished.
For example, if you have done with questions
1 and 3, but not question 2, then
the answer to question 2 is only between
the answers of question 1 and 3.
Just focus on it.
This completion question type has two formats.
Sentence completion, fill in the blanks to complete
the sentence, for example.
And note completion, fill in the blanks to complete the note.
It is the example at the beginning of our lesson.
For completion questions in which the answers might
not come in order, we are going to
divide them into three formats based on the
format of the question.
Table or procedure, image and summary.
For table or procedure, we have table completion,
fill in the blanks to complete a given table, for example.
And flowchart completion, in which you have to
complete a procedure, like this one.
For image, there is only diagram completion.
Finally, we have a completion question type in
which you have to complete a summary.
This has two formats.
Summary completion with wordlist,
which has given words to fill in.
And summary completion without wordlist,
with no given words.
We need to understand some differences between these two,
but we'll learn them in another lesson.
For now, you just need to look at
the following two examples to have an overview about them.
Actually, many of you may think,
why do you give me such a complicated question type
with different formats?
Although there are many formats, the strategy is the same.
So don't worry, you can handle them well.
Let's move on to the steps.
Let's go.
To handle this question type effectively,
please follow my four steps.
Step number one, read the question's requirement carefully.
Step number two, read each question carefully and
predict the answer.
Step number three, apply scanning skills to locate information.
And last, step number four, find and fill in the answer.
Let's analyze them.
Step one, read the question's requirement carefully.
This is a very important step that many candidates skip.
Reading the question's requirements will give us two
following pieces of information.
Format of completion question.
Number of words required for each answer.
For example, let's look at the following questions.
We see that it is table completion.
In the questions, we have complete the table below.
According to the previous part of this lesson,
for this format, the answers might not come in order.
So pay attention to it.
Next, the number of words.
No more than two words, which means you
just write a maximum of two words.
You should underline this phrase because it can
affect your score if the answer you write
has the correct information.
But if it exceeds the word limit, then
it can still be counted as an incorrect answer.
For example, with this word limit, no more
than two words, if the answer is two
months, but you write a period of two
months, then it will not be scored because
the word limit is a maximum of two words.
Your answer includes five words.
If the question's requirement is no more than
two words and or a number, we can
write a maximum of two words and one number.
Step one just needs to be done quickly,
but if you don't do it, you will lose points.
Let's continue with step two.
Step two, read each question carefully and predict the answer.
Every time you handle a question, you should
read it carefully to use prediction skill.
Predict about the answer you need to write.
Prediction skill is very important in completion questions
because making detailed predictions will help you find
the information faster and more correctly.
There are three things you need to predict
for the answer.
Part of speech.
Does the blank need a noun, a verb,
an adjective, or any other parts of speech?
Let's use your grammar to predict it.
Content.
You already have the part of speech.
Now if you can predict the meaning of
the answer, it will be much easier to
find the correct word or words.
For example, is it a noun referring to
a person or a noun referring to an
object or a noun referring to an event?
If it is an adjective, does it have
a positive or negative meaning?
Grammar.
If the answer is a noun, is it a singular or plural noun?
If it is a verb, is it to verb, verb with ing, or verb infinitive?
Step 3.
Apply scanning skills to locate information.
We have learned this skill very carefully at
the beginning of the course and also practiced
in some lessons, so I think you are familiar with it.
I'm going to give you steps for scanning again.
Step 1. Identify keywords in the question.
Step 2. Identify scanning words among keywords.
Step 3. Find keywords, preferably scanning words, or their variations
and synonyms in the passage.
Don't forget some extra tips for scanning when
you find their variations and synonyms.
Tip number 1.
Among scanning words, prefer finding unchangeable keywords,
if possible.
Tip number 2.
Pay attention to other parts of speech of
the original keywords in the scanning process.
Now it's time for the final step.
Step 4. Find and fill in the answer.
Based on the predictions in step 2, we
will find correct answers and then write them
on the answer sheet if you take the paper-based test.
Now we have finished 4 steps for completion questions.
If we do it step by step, this
question type will no longer be difficult for us.
Ok guys, let's take a break before we practice.